Hi everyone!
Hi~~
Today we're going to talk about
咱们今天来聊一个最近几年
a term you've probably heard more frequently
你可能听到越来越频繁的一个词儿
that is
就是
sanctions .
制裁
We'll examine sanctions imposed on five of
我们会通过五个
the most distinctive,
最有特点
influential,
最有影响力
and well-known countries
大家又耳熟能详的国家制裁
understand what they are all about
一边了解一下它到底是怎么回事
At the same time, we'll also explore
同时啊咱们可以一点一点探究一下
the underlying logic of sanctions,
这个制裁的底层逻辑
their methods,
它有哪些手段
how the sanctioned countries can retaliate,
被制裁的国家它能怎么反制
and most importantly, whether
还有最关键的
these sanctions are actually effective.
这个制裁它到底管不管用
First, let me test your knowledge
首先我来考考大家
Do you know which country has been
你知道二战之后
under continuous sanctions for the longest period since World War II ?
被持续制裁时间最长的是哪个国家吗
It's Cuba!
哎就是古巴
In 1959, Castro's revolution
1959年 卡斯特罗领导的革命
overthrew the pro-American Batista government.
推翻了亲美的巴蒂斯塔政府
Cuba embarked on the socialist path,
古巴走上了社会主义道路
adopted a planned economy,
采取计划经济
and became very close to the Soviet Union.
和苏联走的很近
In 1962, the world was shaken by the outbreak of the Cuban Missile Crisis.
1962年爆发了震惊全球的古巴导弹危机
US and the Soviet Union confront each other in Cuba,
美苏在古巴的对峙
nearly triggering World War III.
差点引发了第三次世界大战
Ultimately, the Soviet Union agreed to remove the Cuban Missiles
最终苏联同意撤除古巴导弹
and the US pledged not to invade Cuba.
美国也承诺不入侵古巴
While this averted a hot war
虽说避免了热战
the US immediately played its first
但美国随即第一次高强度
high-intensity card
高烈度的打出了这张牌
economic sanctions
就是经济制裁
Actually before Castro was in power
其实之前自打卡斯特罗上台
the US had already begun sanctioning Cuba
美国就已经开始制裁古巴了
prohibiting oil exports
禁止向古巴出口石油
and reducing sugar import quotas.
减少对它糖的进口配额
However, after the 1962 missile crisis,
但1962年导弹危机之后
the intensity of these sanctions
这个制裁的强度
increased by several orders of magnitude.
一下上升了好几个数量级
In 1963, Kennedy issued
1963年 肯尼迪颁布了
the Cuban Assets Control Act, a
《古巴资产控制条例》的禁令
comprehensive ban on all Cuban imports
全面禁止一切古巴商品的进口
and strict restrictions on exports,
对它的出口也严格限制
thus initiating a complete trade blockade against Cuba.
从此开启了对古巴全面的贸易封锁
These sanctions were quickly escalated
之后很快这个制裁又进一步的升级
they froze Cuban assets in the United States.
古巴在美国的资产也给冻结了
Those Cuban companies in the US were told to
那些在美国的古巴公司都别干了
shut down
封锁
their earnings
你们在美国赚的钱
and savings in the US were frozen
存的钱也冻结
This is essentially the two most
哎你看这个其实就是经济制裁
classic forms of economic sanctions :
两个最经典的手段
trade blockade and asset freezing.
贸易封锁和资产冻结
A trade blockade means I won't buy from you,
贸易封锁就是我不买你东西了
preventing you from making money
不让你赚钱
and I also won't sell to you,
同时我也不卖给你东西了
causing shortages.
让你物资短缺
Asset freezing
而冻结资产呢
means freezing all of
就是你们国家政府的资产
your country's government assets
凡是在我境内的
within my territory.
全都给你冻结
Even if you want to withdraw
就算你想撤走
or do business with others,
你想和其他人做生意
you can't.
也不行
So, how effective are
那你说这么强硬的制裁
these harsh sanctions?
效果它怎么样呢
The answer is
答案是
not so good .
不怎么样
After 1963, Cuba's
古巴1963年之后
economy and foreign trade
不管是经济增长还是对外贸易
continued to grow.
都在持续的增长
Why?
为什么呢
Because it had a powerful backer
哎因为它有个靠山
Soviet Union
就是苏联
The Soviet Union and several socialist countries in Eastern Europe
苏联和当时东欧一些社会主义国家
accounted for three-quarters of Cuba’s foreign trade.
一共占了古巴3/4的对外贸易
They not only being Cuba's largest export market
不光是古巴最大的出口市场
but also providing Cuba with substantial
还给古巴提供了大量的
material and energy subsidies,
物资 能源 补贴等等
especially sugar
尤其是这个糖
At the time, the Soviet Union would import Cuban sugar
当时苏联会以高出市场价6倍的价格
at six times the market price
进口古巴的糖
basically, giving money away.
是吧那基本就是送钱了
With such strong strategic support,
你看这么大力度的这种战略扶持
even under the very nose of the United States,
就算古巴在美国眼皮子底下
the US couldn't do much about it.
美国也拿它没什么办法
However, after the collapse of the Soviet Union, things changed.
但是苏联解体之后就不一样了
Cuba's backers disappeared overnight
古巴的靠山一夜之间消失
and it experienced the most severe economic crisis in its history.
它经历了历史上最严重的经济危机
From 1990 to 1993,
1990年到1993年
its GDP shrank by about one-third,
他的GDP萎缩了大概1/3
foreign trade declined by 60%, there was
对外贸易下降了60%
a severe shortage of goods,
物资极度短缺
many areas experienced power outages for 8 to 16 hours a day,
很多地区每天都要停电8到16个小时
and food supplies were strictly limited
粮食供给也被严格限制
How limited was it
限制到什么程度
The average adult weight in Cuba
当时古巴平均成年人的体重
dropped by 5-10 kilograms.
下降了5-10公斤
You can imagine
你可想而知
how bad that period was for the Cuban economy.
那段时期对古巴的经济来说有多糟糕
There's a specific term in economics
经济学里有个专有名词
called "special period,"
就叫"特殊时期"
it wasn't called Cuba 's special period
他都不叫古巴特殊时期
just special period
就叫特殊时期
You can see how special it was.
你可见他有多特殊
However, despite such a huge impact,
不过哈经受了这么大的冲击
Cuba recovered quickly.
古巴很快就缓过来了
This special period lasted less than five years.
这个特殊时期还不到5年
Especially after 2000
尤其是2,000年之后
look at how rapidly Cuba's GDP grew!
你看古巴这个GDP涨得飞快
Why?
你说为什么呀
Did the US ease sanctions?
是美国放松对它的制裁了吗
Actually, no,
哎其实并没有
it might have even intensified.
反倒可能还加强了
They just made it through
它缓过来呢
Its recovery was due to economic reforms,
当然有它经济改革的原因
such as the rapid development of tourism,
像旅游业发展的很快等等
but there was also a very crucial point
但还有非常关键的一点
it solved a very, very core problem
它解决了一个非常非常核心的问题
energy.
就是能源
Cuba previously relied heavily
古巴之前的能源
on the Soviet Union for energy
主要是靠苏联
but after the collapse of the Soviet Union,
不过苏联解体之后呢
Russia's attitude towards Cuba became very cold.
俄罗斯对古巴的态度一度非常冷淡
So, Cuba sought
所以他就寻觅来寻觅去
a new ally
又找到了一个新朋友
and right in front of it
而且就在眼前
was a major oil producer
还是个石油大户
that is
就是
Venezuela
委内瑞拉
Venezuela too
哎这个委内瑞拉
was later embroiled in sanctions, which
之后也是被制裁整的够呛
we'll discuss later.
我们一会再说
However, since the 1990s,
不过它从90年代开始
it has maintained a very close relationship with Cuba.
就跟古巴走的非常近
Venezuelan President Hugo Chávez and Fidel Castro
委内瑞拉总统查韦斯跟卡斯特罗
had a very good personal relationship.
他俩私人关系就非常好
Chávez often said that Castro
查韦斯经常就说卡斯特罗
was his mentor,
那是我的导师
and he even
他还曾经为了给卡斯特罗一个惊喜
flew to Cuba specifically
专门飞过去
to attend Castro's birthday party as a surprise.
参加卡斯特罗的生日Party
In short, Venezuela
总之委内瑞拉
not only helped Cuba through its most difficult period
不光是帮助古巴度过了最艰难的时期
but also arguably
甚至还可以说是
revitalized Cuba's economy.
推动了古巴经济的再次启动
Actually, relations between the US and Cuba
其实吧美国跟古巴的关系
haven't always been so tense.
并不是一直都那么紧张
In 2009, during Obama's presidency,
2009年开始奥巴马的时候
there was a period of thawing between Cuba and the US,
曾经开启了一段古巴跟美国的解冻期
and the two countries even established diplomatic relations in 2015.
两国甚至还在2015年建交了
But then Trump took office,
谁知道后来特朗普一上台
and Obama's promises no longer held true.
哎奥巴马说的都不算数了啊
Cuba was subject to sanctions again
古巴我们该制裁还要制裁
and it was relisted as
把它再次列入了
a state sponsor of terrorism,
国家支持恐怖主义的名单
with over 200 additional sanctions imposed.
还额外又加了200多条制裁
The US will not lift sanctions against Cuba
我们是不会解除对古巴的制裁的
unless it grants the Cuban people
除非它能把完全的政治自由
complete political freedom .
给到古巴民众
This year, Trump signed a memorandum
今年特朗普又签署了备忘录
to further tighten
将会对古巴
sanctions against Cuba
进一步实施更加严格的制裁
and the US has returned to a pattern of extreme sanctions
美国再次回到了对古巴极限制裁
and embargoes against Cuba.
禁运的模式
I suspect
我估计啊
many people, influenced by media reports,
很多朋友可能受到媒体宣传的影响
feel that Cuba is a poor and underdeveloped country.
就感觉古巴这个国家很穷很落后
It does face humanitarian problems
它确实因为被美国限制物资
due to US restrictions on supplies
有不少人道主义的问题
making it difficult to buy iPhones
也很难买到iPhone
and even access McDonald's.
也很难吃到麦当劳
However, if you look at its GDP growth, as
但你要看它GDP的发展
we just saw,
我们刚才也看到了
the curve is astonishing.
那个曲线是非常惊人的
In 2020, its per capita GDP
2020年人均GDP
approached $10,000,
一度逼近1万美元
surpassing Mexico
赶超了墨西哥
and more than double that of Vietnam.
是越南的两倍多
Overall,
总体来说
its economic growth rate is quite good,
这个经济发展的速度还是挺可以的
seemingly unaffected by the sanctions.
好像没受到制裁那么大的打击
Why?
你说为什么
Well, it's easy to understand.
哎其实也很好理解
Besides the US,
因为除了美国
no other countries
其他的国家
have imposed sanctions on Cuba.
几乎都没有对古巴进行制裁
In fact,
不光没有制裁
most countries
大部分国家
strongly oppose
其实是非常反对
the excessive US sanctions against Cuba.
美国对古巴的过分制裁
For example, in 2024,
你就看2024年
the UN passed a resolution
联合国当时有一项决议
to end US sanctions against Cuba's economy
必须终止美国对古巴的经济
commercial and financial blockade
商业和金融封锁
A voting was held on this
要对这个事投票
resulted in 187 votes in favour,
结果呢是187票赞成
2 against (US and Israel)
2票反对（美国和以色列）
and 1 abstention
还有1票弃权
from Moldova.
是摩尔多瓦
This resolution,
当然这个决议
originating from the UN General Assembly,
它就是出自联合国大会
is not legally binding ;
没有什么强制性
it's merely a recommendation.
就是个建议
However, you can see that
但你能看出来
most countries' stance is very clear:
大多数国家的态度还是非常明确的
this
你现在
is purely humanitarian oppression,
不就是一个纯人道主义压迫了吗
and Cuba hasn't done anything particularly heinous,
古巴也没干什么伤天害理的事
This is a bit unfair.
对吧这有点欺负人了
Anyway, that's the gist of it.
哎反正大概是这么个意思
Currently,
现在呢
Cuba has very close trading partners
古巴跟委内瑞拉 欧盟 中国等等
with Venezuela, the EU, China, and others,
都是非常密切的贸易伙伴
but there's still a significant trade deficit.
但还是有非常严重的贸易逆差
Trade channels aren't very smooth, and
这贸易通道也不是非常的通畅
in the last two years, Cuba has been mired in an economic crisis
最近2年还陷入了经济危机
We'll discuss this in detail
这些我们之后有机会单聊古巴
if we have a chance to talk about Cuba on its own.
再详细展开
What exactly are economic sanctions?
到底什么叫做经济制裁
They are a form of coercion that
它是一种胁迫形式
attempts to force an actor to change their behavior by
试图通过破坏经济交流
disrupting economic exchanges.
而迫使行为者改变其行为
Simply put, it's about making things difficult,
说白了就是我让你难受
causing annoyance,
我让你膈应
and inflicting pain
我让你痛苦
forcing you to compromise
我逼着你做出妥协
and make concessions
做出让步
Economic sanctions
这个经济制裁呢
are generally not an end in themselves,
它一般不是目的
but rather a means
而是一种手段
to deter the other party and achieve certain goals
为了威慑对方达到某种目标
Common goals include
常见的目标有什么呢
policy changes,
比如说政策改变
regime change,
政权更迭
eliminating terrorism,
消除恐怖主义
ending wars
结束战争
human rights, democracy, and so on.
什么人权 民主 其他等等
In the Cuban case,
古巴这个事里头呢
although the US appears to have many goals
虽然表面上美国有很多目标
the most fundamental and core one
但底层最核心的
is regime change.
可以说是政权更迭
From this perspective,
如果从这个角度来看
the US sanctions against Cuba are certainly unsuccessful.
美国对他的制裁肯定是不成功的
In fact, historically,
其实历史上
the percentage of sanctions that actually achieve their objectives
制裁真正能达到目标的
is very low,
比例并不高
less than 10%
还不到10%
But there are successful examples
但成功的也有
A typical one is South Africa.
我能想到的一个比较典型的就是南非
From 1948, it
当时他从1948年开始
implemented apartheid, with
实施种族隔离制度
a minority of whites
少数的白人
ruling over the majority of blacks and people of colour.
统治多数的黑人和有色人种
Later, in the 1980s,
后来80年代的时候
almost all countries in the world unified
全球各个国家几乎是统一
in imposing economic sanctions on South Africa
对南非实施经济制裁
cutting off its trade
切断它的贸易
and aid.
切断它的援助
You have to understand that South Africa was heavily reliant on its gold and
你要知道
mineral exports,
矿产出口
so this blow was very powerful.
这打击就很有力
Coupled with external public opinion pressure and
再加上外部的舆论压力
internal resistance movements,
内部的反抗运动
it successfully forced the South African government
成功逼迫南非政府
to release Mandela in 1990,
在1990年释放了曼德拉
gradually abolishing apartheid.
逐渐取消了种族隔离的制度
Then the West slowly eased its sanctions.
然后西方也慢慢放开了对它的制裁
This is a very successful example.
这就是个很成功的例子
You see,
你看南非
the main difference between South Africa and Cuba
它跟古巴最主要的一个不同
is that other countries pulled in.
就是是其他国家拉起手来一起制裁
The effect of sanctions greatly amplifies
这个制裁的力度就大大增强
However, even with global cooperation,
不过就算全球国家拉起手来一起制裁
some countries can withstand the pressure.
也有国家它能扛得住
Even the US, which only intends to sanction
而就算美国它就打算自己制裁
one country, has its own
一个人制裁
methods.
他也有招
But wait,
哎别急哈
we'll see soon enough.
这个马上一会就能看到
Cuba
你看古巴
has been sanctioned for years, and
被制裁了这么多年
its economy is actually still relatively stable.
经济其实还算OK
But its close ally,
但是我们刚才提到它那个好哥们
Venezuela,
委内瑞拉
After being sanctioned
那受到制裁之后
has become one of the worst-performing
真的就成了全世界几乎是
economies in the world
经济最差最糟糕的国家
Venezuela has the world's
你想委内瑞拉
largest proven oil reserves,
那是全球已探明石油储量里边
and should
最大的国家
theoretically be
按理说怎么着
one of the richest countries in
也应该是20世纪
the 20th century.
全球最有钱的国家之一
Instead, it's in complete chaos.
结果搞得一团乱
Let's talk about what happened in Venezuela.
咱来说说委内瑞拉怎么回事
In 2005, the US began sanctions against Venezuela.
2005年 美国开始了对委内瑞拉的制裁
Initially, the sanctions imposed on Venezuela were not very broad
但最开始制裁范围其实并不是很广
Mostly about
大概就是说哎
widespread drug abuse
你们那边毒品有点泛滥了哈
combating terrorism
而且打击恐怖主义
poor cooperation
你们也不怎么配合怎么搞
Individuals were being targeted
所以就针对一些个人啊
including government officials
包括政府官员
adding up to dozens of people
加起来大概几十个
and sanction was imposed
采取了一些制裁
Later,
后来呢
due to Venezuela's dire economic situation and
因为委内瑞拉经济实在是太糟糕了
severe inflation,
通货膨胀极其严重
the public could no longer tolerate
民众开始受不了
leading to nearly ten thousand
在2014年爆发了全国范围的抗议活动
nationwide protests in 2014.
大大小小加起来有近万起
Maduro
规模空前
responded with a strong crackdown
而当时马杜罗对这些抗议
on these protests,
进行了非常强力的镇压
which the United States deemed
哎美国这边就认为
a human rights violation by the Venezuelan government.
这个事
This prompted the US to impose sanctions and pressure,
立刻开始制裁施压
and Obama signed
奥巴马就签署了
the "Venezuela Human Rights and Civil Society Protection Act of 2014"
《2014年委内瑞拉保护人权和公民社会法案》
began imposing sanctions on more government officials
开始对更多的政府官员和官方实体
and official entities
实施制裁
but so far
但直到这
it has remained a targeted attack on individuals.
都还是那种针对个人的精准打击
As we mentioned earlier,
刚才我们也说了
sanction methods
制裁的手段
typically include trade sanctions and asset freezes,
一般有贸易制裁和资产冻结
which are already quite severe.
其实这都是已经很严重的制裁手段了
However sanctions
而制裁呢
usually don't start so severely;
他一般开始的时候都不会这么严重
they usually begin with certain individuals, entities, or
都是会先从一些个人或者某些实体
companies.
某些公司开始
This may not have a significant impact
这种对于扭转整个事件
on reversing the overall situation
作用不一定那么大
it only targets those individuals.
只是打击那些个体
And these targeted individuals
而这些被打击的个体呢
are usually very powerful domestically, making
一般在国内都是那种非常有权势的
them difficult to target.
他也很难被打击到
Therefore, it becomes symbolic,
所以他就变成一种象征性
expressing a tough stance,
也是表达一种强硬的态度
as if to say, "Don't let me catch you,
感觉就是说你可别让我逮着了啊
or else
你要让我逮着
you’ll pay for it"
要你好看
In 2014,
你看 2014年
the sanctions imposed on Venezuela
对委内瑞拉的制裁
weren't just imposed by the US,
其实不光是美国
Canada, the EU, the UK, joined in
加拿大 欧盟 英国等等也都制裁
but they were relatively restrained,
但都是那种比较克制
targeting individuals or certain weapons.
就针对个人或者针对一些武器的制裁
But then came
但之后 谁来了
Trump.
特朗普
At the start of his first term, he began to exert pressure.
他第一任任期一上来就开始发力
In 2017,
2017年
the US began imposing sanctions
美国开始对委内瑞拉整个国家层面
on Venezuela at the national level,
实施制裁
prohibiting its bonds from trading in the US market
禁止它的债券在美国市场交易
essentially preventing it from accessing the US financial market.
就是不让你进入美国的金融市场
Some might think this sounds alright
有些人可能感觉这听起来也还好
It's just preventing it from financing in the US, right?
对吧不就是不让你在美国融资了吗
But let me tell you,
但我跟你说
this is actually extremely detrimental to Venezuela.
这个其实对委内瑞拉来说非常要命
The US essentially orchestrated a precise strike.
美国相当于是设计好的一个精准打击
On who?
打击谁呢
It's Venezuela's state-owned oil company, PDVSA.
就是委内瑞拉的国家石油公司PDVSA
We all know that fossil fuels
我们都知道这种化石能源
like oil and natural gas
石油天然气
are crucial for countries
对于这种化石能源国家来说
that rely heavily on them.
是非常重要的
Such as Iran and Russia.
你像伊朗 俄罗斯都是
However, oil is even more important for Venezuela
但是石油对于委内瑞拉
especially to the government
尤其是对于委内瑞拉政府来说
It's more important
它更重要
because Venezuela's economy is in dire straits.
因为委内瑞拉的经济实在是太糟糕了
Government revenue comes almost entirely from oil.
政府的收入几乎是完全来自石油
While Iran and Russia
你像伊朗 俄罗斯
at least have relatively well-established economic frameworks
好歹人经济框架是比较成型的
whether above-ground or underground,
你甭管是地上的还是地下
whatever their structure—
甭管他什么结构
they have their own set of operating rules.
人家是有一套自己的运行规则的
But Venezuela's economy
但委内瑞拉这边 基本除了石油
aside from oil, is essentially a disorganized mess.
其他经济那完全就是散架的散装的
It has such a significant weakness that
它有一个这么好的软肋
the US naturally targeted it,
美国自然是要瞄准了打
starting with financial sanctions,
首先就是金融制裁
because its oil companies
因为他的石油公司
were previously heavily reliant on the US financial market.
之前是非常依赖美国的金融市场
The company seeking financing
来融资的
was excluded, its cash flow
这个被排除在外
was immediately disrupted,
资金链一下被卡壳了
and its external trade activities
跟外部的贸易活动
became virtually impossible.
几乎就没有办法进行
Later, in 2019,
后来2019年
the US
美国又进一步
imposed further sanctions
对委内瑞拉这个石油公司
on the Venezuelan oil company,
实施额外的制裁
such as blocking payments
比如阻止付款
and freezing assets
冻结资产
As a sanctioned country,
那作为这个被制裁国呢
its usual countermeasures are not hard to imagine
通常他反制的方式也不难想象
it quickly seeks other buyers,
就是我赶紧去找其他的买家
finding alternative buyers
找一些替代买家
With such a scarce resource as oil, if
你像石油这么稀缺的资源
the US sanctions me,
美国制裁我
Europe sanctions me—
欧洲制裁我
there will always be someone who needs it.
那总有人需要
Even if it's a bit troublesome
就算麻烦一点
but in most cases,
但大部分情况下
alternative buyers can be found;
应该是能找着替代买家的
it won't be completely blocked.
他不会完全被堵死
You see, after Venezuela was sanctioned,
你看委内瑞拉被制裁之后
President Maduro
总统马杜罗
immediately moved the oil company's European office
就立刻把石油公司的欧洲办事处
from Lisbon to Moscow
从里斯本迁到了莫斯科
and began to sell a large amount of crude oil to Russia,
然后开始把大量的原油卖给俄罗斯
which then resells it to other countries
通过俄罗斯再转卖给其他国家
primarily India.
这里头很主要的就是印度
However,
但是呢
these alternative solutions are more expensive
毕竟这些替代的方案成本更高
and have limited demand.
需求其实也有限
Therefore, after the sanctions,
所以被制裁之后
Venezuela's oil revenue plummeted,
委内瑞拉的原油收入暴跌
with government revenue as a percentage of GDP
政府收入占GDP的比例
falling from around 30%
从原来30%左右
to less than 10%.
跌到了不到10%
Simultaneously, its financing channels were blocked by the US.
同时融资渠道也给美国堵上了
Imagine if your
你就想要是你
income were cut by a third,
收入一下被砍了1/3
and loans were restricted
贷款也被限制了
small loans, consumer loans, all were off-limits—
什么小额贷 消费贷 全都不让用了
you'd definitely cut all unnecessary expenses.
那肯定你一些非必要的开支全砍了
If a chair leg breaks,
要是椅子腿断了
you'll prop it up with stones;
那就咱拿石头垫着
if you catch a cold
要是感冒了
you'll bear it ;
那就自己扛着
if a light bulb burns out
要是灯泡坏了
you'll go to bed early
那就早点睡觉
if the toilet breaks
要是马桶坏了
you'll use a public restroom.
那就去公共厕所
Venezuela is pretty much the same
委内瑞拉也差不多
They began drastically cutting spending on
它就开始大量削减民生类的开销
basic necessities and infrastructure maintenance,
基础设施维护的开销
leading to severe aging of many infrastructure projects,
导致他国内很多基础设施都严重老化
frequent power outages, and
也经常停电
difficulties maintaining the water, sanitation, and healthcare systems.
自来水 卫生 医疗系统都难以维持
Venezuela's economy completely collapsed,
委内瑞拉的经济完全崩溃
with inflation exceeding 300,000 percent in 2019.
2019年的通货膨胀率超过了百分之三十万
Recently, relations between the US and Venezuela have become even more tense.
最近美国跟委内瑞拉的关系更加紧张
The US, citing "drugs,"
美国以"毒品"为名
has bombed several Venezuelan ships.
炸了好几艘委内瑞拉的船只
The State Department and the Department of Justice have also offered a $50 million
国务院和司法部还悬赏5,000万美元
reward for information
给提供任何线索
leading to the arrest or conviction of Maduro
导致逮捕或定罪马杜罗的人
The official reasons
美国这么针对马杜罗
given by the US for targeting Maduro
官方的理由是俩
are twofold: his alleged involvement in drugs
一个是说他涉及毒品
and his alleged suppression of democracy.
一个是说他扼杀民主
However, in all fairness, given
不过呢公理公道讲
his dire economic situation,
他经济这么糟糕
we cannot solely blame sanctions,
咱不能全赖制裁
and even sanctions alone
甚至制裁在这里头
cannot address this issue.
真的就是很小的原因
We definitely won't go into detail about that today
但这个我们肯定今天不展开讲了
To be honest,
说实在的
the countries we've talked about today
今天我们说到的这些国家
are all very interesting
都非常的有意思
even quite bizarre.
甚至可以说很奇葩
We'll dedicate a separate episode to them if we have the chance.
有机会我们都是要单独开一期讲的
But today,
但今天呢
our focus is still on sanctions.
我们核心还是围绕着制裁说
After entering hyperinflation,
进入到恶性通胀之后
for ordinary people,
对于他的普通人来说
water and electricity outages are commonplace.
断水断电就是家常便饭
The banknotes are so hot to hold
那个纸币拿在手里都是真烫手
that they feel like they need to queue for a whole day to buy food.
恨不得立马就去排一天队买粮食
But even though the situation is already so bad,
但即便情况已经这么糟糕了
it can be said that sanctions have
可以说制裁已经把委内瑞拉的经济
pushed Venezuela's economy into an abyss.
推向了深渊
But at least so far,
可是至少到目前为止
the purpose of these sanctions has not been achieved
这个制裁的目的依然没有达到
Maduro is still the president.
马杜罗还是总统
Look at the examples of Venezuela and Cuba, and
你看委内瑞拉和古巴这俩例子
we have found a very important underlying principle
我们已经发现了一个非常重要的规律
is that economic sanctions
就是经济制裁
regardless of who they target
你甭管是针对谁
it ultimately directly oppress
其实最终更多直接压迫的
the lives of the lower classes in the sanctioned country.
是被制裁国底层人民的生活
The cruel logic behind this
这背后非常残酷的逻辑
is the hope that by oppressing the lower classes and
就是希望通过压迫底层人民
the masses, they
压迫大众
can drive internal change within the sanctioned country.
去推动被制裁国的内部变革
In fact, both
其实这一点
the sanctioning
不管是制裁国
and sanctioned countries' elites
还是被制裁国的精英阶层
are well aware of this
他们都心知肚明
which is quite ironic, isn't it?
这就挺讽刺的是吧
Because often, the reason for sanctions is that
因为很多时候制裁的原因就是因为
the sanctioned country suppresses democracy and
你被制裁国压制民主
violates human rights.
侵犯人权
So, how about this:
那要不这样吧
I'll further oppress your lives,
我来进一步压迫你们的生活
making you even more miserable,
让你更水深火热
to increase your determination to resist,
来帮你增加一点反抗的决心
right?
是吧嗯
Let's leave it at that.
这个分析我们就点到为止
We'll look at the next country,
我们来看下一个国家
North Korea.
朝鲜
The sanctions against North Korea
其实对朝鲜的制裁
mainly revolve around nuclear weapons
主要就是围绕着核武器
or more precisely, it's about
或者更严格一点说
weapons of mass destruction.
是大规模杀伤性武器
In 1994, the United States and North Korea reached the Agreed Framework on nuclear issues
1994年 美国和朝鲜达成了核框架协议
with North Korea agreeing to freeze its nuclear program
朝鲜同意冻结它的核计划
and accept monitoring by the International Atomic Energy Agency
并且接受国际原子能机构的监控
The US, in turn, provided two light-water reactors
美国呢则提供两座轻水反应堆
oil, and
提供石油
gradually liberalised its economy.
逐步放开它的经济
However, this agreement didn't last long;
但这个协议并没有持续多久
relations collapsed in 2002,
双方在2002年关系就崩了
with both sides accusing the other of
双方都指责对方说
failing to fulfill its obligations under the agreement
你没有履行协议的义务
We won't go into the details,
这个我们具体就不掰扯了
but the agreement broke down,
总之协议破裂
and North Korea
朝鲜在2003年
withdrew from the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons in 2003.
退出《不扩散核武器条约》
Afterwards,
在那之后
China, Japan, North Korea, South Korea, Russia, and the United States
中国 日本 朝鲜 韩国 俄罗斯 美国
held multiple rounds of the Six-Party Talks
针对朝鲜核问题
regarding the North Korean nuclear issue,
进行了多轮的"六方会谈"
but it was difficult to reach a substantial agreement.
但很难达成实质性协议
In 2006, North Korea conducted its first nuclear test,
2006年 朝鲜首次进行了核试验
shocking the world.
震惊全世界
The UN Security Council immediately passed Resolution 1718,
联合国安理会立刻通过了1718号决议
imposing economic, military, and trade sanctions on North Korea.
对朝鲜实施经济 军事 贸易制裁
In short,
从那之后
since then,
我们简单来说
North Korea has continued to conduct nuclear tests,
就是朝鲜不停地进行核试验
and the UN has continuously increased sanctions against it.
各国联合国不断对朝鲜加大制裁
Every time North Korea conducts a test or launches a missile,
朝鲜一实验一发射导弹
the UN passes a new sanctions package,
联合国就通过新的制裁方案
including personal asset sanctions, financial sanctions,
什么个人资产 金融制裁
and trade sanctions
贸易制裁等等全用上
at least eight resolutions have been passed
至少通过了8次决议
to expand sanctions against North Korea
扩大对朝鲜的制裁
You should know that
哎你要知道啊
the UN rarely imposes sanctions on
联合国它其实是很少对一个国家整体
a country as a whole
或者是对这个国家的政府
or on its government;
去进行制裁的
most of the time it targets individuals
大部分时候是针对一些个人
or entities.
或者一些实体
Why?
为什么呢
Firstly, imposing sanctions on an entire country
一方面你要整体制裁
would be too strong and overwhelming;
这个力度确实是太强太大了
secondly
另一方面呢
the UN Security Council is
也是联合国安理会
sometimes
它大部分时候
it's difficult to reach a consensus.
很难达成一个统一的意见
For the UN Security Council
你想要是联合国安理会
to pass a sanctions resolution,
通过一个制裁决议的话
it requires a majority vote of all 15 member states.
必须15个成员国多数通过
More importantly,
更关键的是
it's rare for the five permanent members
这五个常任理事国没有否决
not to veto it.
这就很少见
For example, in 2022,
你比如说2022年的时候
US attempted to push for
美国其实尝试推动联合国
expanded UN sanctions against North Korea
扩大对朝鲜的制裁
but this was vetoed by China and Russia.
但是就被中国和俄罗斯给否了
In short,
总之呢
UN's numerous rounds of sanctions against North Korea
联合国对朝鲜这么多轮的制裁
are arguably among
从限制范围来说
the most severe globally in terms of scope.
可以说是全球最严厉的制裁之一
Yet, North Korea
而朝鲜呢
continues to act unilaterally.
这边依然是我行我素
You impose your sanctions,
你制裁你的哎
I'll just keep doing mine.
我实验我的
Look, since 2012, during Kim Jong-un's administration,
你看从2012年金正恩时期开始
the number of missiles North Korea has launched has increased significantly.
朝鲜发射导弹的数量明显增加
Isn't that surprising?
这不奇怪吗
As we just mentioned,
我们刚才也说了
sanctions require the cooperation of many countries.
制裁需要很多国家联合起来
Its effect is much stronger
它这个效果才更强
As for North Korea
而对朝鲜
The UN has imposed joint sanctions
联合国这边已经联合制裁了
but North Korea hasn't been deterred;
但朝鲜没有被威慑到
instead, it has launched more missiles.
反而发射更多的导弹
Why is it so defiant?
你说它为什么这么刚呢
Well, on one hand,
哎 一方面啊
it does indeed have a strong desire for nuclear weapons.
确实它对核武器非常的渴望
But a crucial point
还有很关键的一点
is why sanctions aren't as effective
制裁为什么对它没有那么有效
North Korea is extremely closed off.
因为朝鲜非常的封闭
Since World War II,
二战之后
North Korea has been
朝鲜一直可以说
one of the world's most closed economies.
是全球最封闭的经济体之一
It was relatively better during the Cold War, but
冷战时期相对还好一点
after the collapse of the Soviet Union,
苏联解体之后
North Korea became even more closed off.
朝鲜就更封闭了
Think about it:
你想啊
the essence of sanctions is to isolate a country
制裁的本质就是孤立一个国家
but North Korea has already isolated itself first.
但朝鲜自己就先把自己给孤立起来了
Therefore, imposing sanctions
再施加制裁
on it is bound to be less effective.
效果肯定就没那么理想
In 2017, North Korea's exports as a percentage of GDP
2017年 朝鲜的出口占GDP的比例
had been reduced to only 1%.
已经被压到只有1%了
You need to know this figure
你要知道这个数字
countries with rates below 10% are very rare;
低于10%的国家都非常少见
many European countries exceed 40%
很多欧洲国家都超过了40%
with Singapore and the UAE exceeding 100%,
像什么新加坡 阿联酋都超过100%
while North Korea's is only 1%.
而朝鲜 只有1%
Actually, North Korea has many ways to circumvent sanctions,
其实朝鲜也有很多规避制裁的方式了
such as smuggling
比如说走私
and building its own hacker team
又构建自己的黑客队伍
for money laundering.
洗钱网络
I'll tell you, North Korean hackers
我跟你说朝鲜的黑客
are quite skilled.
还是非常厉害的
According to preliminary estimates
据不完全统计
in the past eight years
近8年间
they have launched dozens of large-scale cyberattacks
发起了数十起大型的网络攻击
profiting over $3 billion.
获利超过30亿美元
But regardless,
但不管怎么说
North Korea's trade with the outside world is still very limited.
朝鲜跟外界的贸易往来还是非常少的
Speaking of which,
哎说到这儿
let me test you.
我来考考大家哈
Do you know what
你知道朝鲜在现在
North Korea's main export product,
全球疯狂制裁的重压之下
accounting for 40% of its exports in 2023,
它最近几年最主要的出口产品
is under the heavy pressure
占了它2023年出口40%
of global sanctions?
你知道是什么吗
Here are a few options:
来给你几个选项啊
A. Ore
A. 矿石
B. Toys
B. 玩具
C. Automobiles
C. 汽车
D. None of the above
D. 以上都不对
The answer is
哎答案就是
The remaining items are
其实剩下几个
also some of North Korea's major exports,
也是朝鲜比较主要的出口产品了
especially raw ores.
尤其是原矿石
But its largest export product,
但它出口最多的产品
which I find quite amusing,
我觉得还挺逗的哈
is wigs
是假发
including human hair, beards,
就包括人的假头发胡须
and false eyelashes.
还有假睫毛
In 2023, North Korea exported
2023年 朝鲜向中国出口了
1,680 tons of wigs to China.
1,680吨的假发
To put that into perspective,
这是什么概念
I roughly estimated
我粗略估算了一下哈
that it's equivalent to
这大概相当于
the hair volume of 150 million adult women with long hair.
1.5亿个成年的长发女性的发量
North Korea's total population is
就是我这种
only about 26 million;
朝鲜的总人口才2,600多万
let's assume half of them are women.
我们就假设这里边一半是女性
The amount of wigs it exports annually
它每年出口的假发量
is enough to shave all the women in the country ten times over!
够把全国的女性剃光十回的了
How is that possible?
这怎么可能
Where does it get so many wigs every year?
对吧它一年哪来那么多假发
Of course, some people
当然有人猜说
speculate that it doesn't actually export real human hair.
它其实出口的不是真人的头发
That's certainly possible
哎确实可能有这种情况发生
but the main reason
但主要哈
is that it first imports
是因为它会先去进口
"raw hair" from other countries,
别的国家的"原发"
just like with oil.
就跟石油似的
You import crude oil
你进口原油
and then refine it
然后精炼
For hair, I need to import raw hair.
头发我得进口原发
For North Korea,
对于朝鲜来说
it mainly buys from India
它主要是从印度买
processes it,
然后过来加工
and then
我把它整理整理
packages or assembles it into various hair accessories
打包好或者粘成各种发饰
before exporting it globally.
然后出口到全球
Generally, it first goes through China
一般呢会先通过中国
So you see, in 2023
所以你看
North Korea's largest import
朝鲜在2023年进口的第一大产品
was hair
也是头发
The next country we're going to talk about
好我们要说的下一个被制裁国
that was sanctioned actually
其实它呢
had successful negotiations before
之前的制裁是有过成功的谈判结果
and more than once
而且还不止一次
that is Iran
就是伊朗
We've discussed the Iranian economy separately;
伊朗经济我们单开说过啊
today we'll mainly talk about the sanctions
今天我们主要是针对制裁来聊聊
In 1979,
1979年
Khomeini, the Islamic leader, had just successfully
伊斯兰领袖霍梅尼刚刚革命成功
overthrown the Pahlavi dynasty
巴列维王朝被推翻
and established the Islamic Republic of Iran.
建立了伊朗伊斯兰共和国
The Pahlavi king fled overseas,
巴列维国王跑到了海外
and then the famous hostage crisis occurred.
紧接着就发生了著名的人质危机
A group of Islamic students
一帮伊斯兰学生
stormed the US embassy in Tehran,
冲进了美国驻德黑兰大使馆
taking dozens of American diplomats hostage and
把几十个美国使馆的外交官扣做人质
demanding the US hand over Pahlavi.
要求美方配合交出巴列维
At that time, relations between Iran and the US were very tense,
当时伊朗跟美国关系非常紧张
and the US imposed
美国就对伊朗实施了
very severe economic sanctions on Iran
非常严厉的经济制裁
freezing $8.1 billion of Iranian assets in the US.
冻结了伊朗在美国81亿美元的资产
This was extremely devastating for Iran at the time,
这对当时的伊朗来说是非常要命的
and it also prohibited many of
同时还禁止了很多
Iran's economic and trade exchanges
伊朗的经济贸易往来
You have to understand
哎你要知道哈
back then,
在那时候
economic sanctions weren't
经济制裁这个手牌
as common as they are now;
不像现在这么烂大街
the US hadn't used them much except for Cuba.
美国除了对古巴以外就没怎么用过
Iran honestly wasn’t prepared for that tactic
伊朗着实它也没怎么见过这招
and unsure of its consequences
也不知道会带来什么样的后果
so they were extremely cautious,
所以也是非常谨慎
employing
非常小心
various negotiations
再叠加上各种的谈判
and threats .
各种威胁
After more than a year,
一年多以后
Iran released the US embassy personnel.
伊朗就释放了美国的使馆人员
This action, while contributing
你看这里头有一部分功劳
to the sanctions, can indeed be considered
确实是可以算在制裁里头的
a short-lived
可以算是一次短暂
but successful case.
但是成功的制裁案例
In the following decades,
在接下来的几十年里
As the Iran-Iraq War progressed, support for regional armed groups
随着两伊战争支持地区武装组织
missile programs, and other initiatives gradually came to light
导弹项目等等逐渐浮出水面
the US began to intensify its sanctions against Iran.
美国就开始不断加大对伊朗的制裁
However, this period was relatively restrained,
不过这个时期其实一直还比较克制
primarily targeting individuals,
主要针对个人
armed groups
针对武装组织
or oil companies.
或者针对石油公司等等
The real large-scale sanctions against Iran
而真正对伊朗大规模制裁的
began after 2000, when
还是在2,000年之后
there were indications that
当时就有迹象表明
Iran was secretly conducting nuclear tests
伊朗正在秘密进行核试验
Once nuclear weapons are involved,
哎一旦涉及到核武器
global sanctions intensify,
全球制裁力度都会加大
just like with North Korea
就跟朝鲜一样
Not only the US,
不光是美国
but also the EU
像是欧盟
and the UN Security Council began sanctioning Iran.
联合国安理会也都开始制裁伊朗
And this time, I'm telling you,
而这回我跟你说
the US has pulled a more ruthless move
美国它来了一招更狠的
the second form of sanctions.
可以说是制裁的第二式
This is crucial
这个很关键
and became a hallmark of its subsequent
也成了它之后
comprehensive economic sanctions.
全面经济制裁的一个标配
This is secondary sanctions.
就是二级制裁
What are secondary sanctions?
什么叫二级制裁
It's not just about
他不光是说
escalating the situation.
我上升了一个等级那么简单
It means not only that I won't do business with you anymore,
他是说不光我不和你做生意了
but I'll also threaten others
同时我还会威胁其他人
if I find out anyone
就是你们谁要是让我发现
dares to do business with them, I'll deal with them too.
敢和他做生意 我也要来弄你
It's like a group of kids.
这就好像有一帮小朋友
Previous sanctions were like the US threatening Iran, saying
之前的制裁是说大美威胁小伊
"I'm not playing with you anymore
说我不跟你玩了
you can't touch anything I've used,
往后我用过的东西
any toys I've played with,
我玩过的玩具
or any seat I've sat in.
我坐过的位置你都不能碰
You 'd better avoid me."
以后见着我你就绕道走
See, that threat sounds very tough.
你看啊
But even with its strong economy, the US only
但是呢美国它经济实力再强
accounts for a quarter of the world's GDP.
也就占了全世界GDP的1/4
If you just threaten to stop playing with them,
你光威胁说我不和你玩了
Iran can still play with the other three-quarters of the kids, right?
那小伊还可以跟剩下那3/4的小朋友玩
It can still play with Europe, Russia, Japan,
对吧他还可以跟小欧 小俄 小日们玩
and do business with those countries.
和那些国家做生意
So the effect of those previous sanctions wasn't very obvious.
所以之前这个制裁的效果不是很明显
But this time, secondary sanctions
而这回这个二级制裁呢
are like the US saying,
就相当于大美那些说了
"Not only am I not playing with Iran,
不光我不跟小伊玩了
but you other countries
你们其他人
Europe, Russia, Japan
小欧 小俄 小日
can't play with Iran either.
你们也不能跟小伊玩了啊
Anyone who dares to play with them,
谁要敢跟他玩
I'll deal with them"
我干你
You see, the US is the leader of the kids, right
你想这个大美本来就是孩子王对吧
He also has the largest muscle mass.
肌肉量也最大
Other kids
其他小朋友
generally
一般情况下
don't need to go against the US.
他也犯不着跟大美对着干
Anyway, I'm probably not very familiar with Iran
反正我可能跟小伊也不太熟
so I won't play with Iran
那我也别和小伊玩了
You see, secondary sanctions
你看二级制裁
are about threatening other countries to isolate together
就是通过威胁其他国家跟我一起孤立
which greatly increases the success rate of the sanctions.
就会大大提高制裁的成功率
For the US,
对美国来说
it's like leverage
它相当于一个杠杆
the impact is much greater.
这个打击力度就要大得多
Let's analyse further.
咱们来进一步分析
Actually , there's a prerequisite
其实能实施二级制裁
for implementing secondary sanctions
这里头有一个先决条件
the US
就是你这个大美 美国
itself must first be extremely powerful.
你首先自己得非常的强大
Look at the number of sanctions in history
你看历史上这些制裁的数量
you'll find that after year 2000
你会发现2,000年之后
it increased exponentially.
它是指数上升
You might ask why
你说为什么
Is it because
是因为2,000年之后
the world is much more chaotic after year 2000
世界比之前乱的多吗
Oh, not necessarily
哦未必
One major reason
很主要的一个原因
is that the world has shifted from a bipolar to
就是这个世界从原来的两极
a unipolar system,
变成了后来的单极
U.S. hegemony
美国一家独大
making it easier for the US
就会让它更容易
to implement secondary sanctions.
去实施二级制裁
This significantly increases the effectiveness of
有效性就会大大提升
US sanctions, leading to a greater frequency of their use.
导致美国会增加使用制裁的频率
For example, Venezuela, which we just discussed,
比如说我们刚刚说的委内瑞拉
is severely restricted by sanctions,
为什么被制裁限制的那么惨
primarily due to secondary sanctions
其实主要也是二级制裁
not trade, but
不过不是贸易
financial secondary sanction
而是金融的二级制裁
Any other country
你们其他国家
trading with Venezuela
谁要是跟委内瑞拉进行贸易往来
cannot access US banks.
你们不能碰美国的银行
This has a very wide reach,
这个打击面是非常大的
resulting in almost no one
这就会导致几乎没有人
daring to have financial dealings with Venezuela,
敢跟委内瑞拉有资金往来
at least not openly.
至少明面上有资金往来
In short,
总之
in 2010, the US imposed even harsher sanctions on Iran
2010年美国对伊朗实施了更严厉的制裁
The UN sanctions
再加上联合国的制裁
dealt a heavy blow to Iran
让伊朗遭受了沉重的打击
forcing it back to the negotiating table.
也迫使他又回到了谈判桌上
Starting in 2013, negotiation with various major powers
从2013年开始跟各个大国谈判
culminated in the
终于在2015年
signing of the famous Iran nuclear deal in 2015.
签订了著名的伊朗核协议
Iran agreed to limit some of its nuclear activities
伊朗同意限制部分的核活动
in exchange for a reduction in sanctions
来换取制裁的缓解
This agreement
哎这个协议
can be considered
可以说是
a highlight in the history of economic sanctions negotiations
经济制裁谈判史上的一个高光时刻
sanctions finally led to peace, and
制裁终于是和平的推动了
a major agreement was reached.
一个重大协议的达成
Iran did indeed receive some economic relief,
伊朗果然得到了一些经济上的缓解
with some assets unfrozen
部分资产被解冻
and oil exports beginning to recover
石油出口也开始恢复
However, this didn't last long.
但是好景不长
Then came the revelation
接下来谁来了
the previous agreement with Iran
这伊朗之前的协议
was a terrible deal, and
是一个非常糟糕的deal
they reneged
我们反悔了
reinstating and even
重新开始对伊朗制裁
intensifying sanctions against Iran ,
而且还加重了
causing a precipitous drop in oil exports.
导致伊朗的石油出口断崖式下跌
This year, negotiations between Iran and the UN are on the verge of collapse.
今年伊朗跟联合国的谈判也濒临崩溃
The UN reinstated sanctions
联合国刚刚在今年9月份
against Iran in September.
恢复了对伊朗的制裁
We've discussed Iran's methods of evading sanctions
而伊朗躲避制裁的方式
in detail before.
我们之前也详细聊过
Over time,
其实这么长时间
it has developed
它已经可以说是形成了
its own countermeasures system.
自己的一套反制的体系
Through its ghost fleet at sea and
通过海上的幽灵舰队
smuggling networks, it
通过走私网络
has mitigated the intensity of sanctions to some extent
一定程度上缓解了制裁的烈度
significantly strengthening
使得它控制经济的两只大手
its two major economic arms
革命卫队和基金会
the Revolutionary Guard and the Foundation.
力量得到了大幅的加强
However, its overall economy is severely suppressed
但整体的经济在美国制裁的重压之下
under the heavy pressure of US sanctions
是被严重压制的
especially after the pandemic,
尤其是在疫情之后
plunging into a severe food crisis,
陷入了非常严重的粮食危机
energy crisis
能源危机
and hyperinflation.
还有恶性通货膨胀
The riyal's continued plunge in exchange rate
里亚尔的汇率持续暴跌
confirms
你看这是不是又印证了
our earlier theory that
我们刚才说的那个理论
sanctions further suppress Iran's lower classes.
制裁更多压制了伊朗的底层大众
Even if you believe
就算你认为
this is a necessary price to pay to achieve our goals,
这是我们达成目标必须要付出的代价
and that the lower classes must be suppressed to a certain extent
底层大众就是得被压制到一定程度
before they can rise up and make changes
才能站起来做出些改变
However,
但是呢
there's an even harsher reality
这里边其实还有一个更残酷的现实
often,
就是很多时候
and most of the time,
也可以说是大部分时候
sanctions not only fail
制裁不光是达不到
to create internal conflict within the sanctioned country,
让被制裁国内部产生对立的效果
but their propaganda actually
反倒是在它的宣传下
makes the lower classes more hostile to the sanctioning country.
会让底层的大众更敌视制裁国
The sanctioned government
而被制裁国的政府
often uses this environment to
通常会在这种特殊环境下
further strengthen its authoritarianism
进一步增强它的集权
This has a counterproductive effect,
你看这其实起到的是一个反效果
making change more difficult,
让做出改变 变得更加困难
and the main consequence of sanctions
让制裁的主要后果
becomes
就变成了
simply punishing and suppressing
单纯的去惩罚和压制
the lower classes of the sanctioned country.
被制裁国的底层大众
Okay, next,
好接下来
the last sanctioned country we'll discuss
我们要说的最后一个被制裁的国家
is a comprehensive summary
可以说是刚才我们说到的
of all the methods we've mentioned.
这些方式的一个大汇总大总结
The US and EU
美国 欧盟
have basically used all their sanctioning tactics
基本上把这么多年制裁的看家本领
over the years on it.
都用他身上了
I'm sure you've guessed it
想必大家也都猜出来了
it's Russia.
就是俄罗斯
Before the Russo-Ukrainian war,
其实在俄乌战争之前
in 2014, Russia annexed Crimea, and many countries and regions, including
2014年俄罗斯占领克里米亚开始
the US, EU, Canada, Australia, and
包括美国 欧盟 加拿大 澳大利亚
Japan,
日本在内
imposed sanctions on Russia.
很多国家地区都对俄罗斯实施了制裁
At the time, this was considered very severe;
这个其实在当时看来已经非常严厉了
in terms of the number of sanctioned items,
从被制裁的项目数量来看
the largest at that time was Iran
那时候最多的是伊朗
has 3,616 sanctions,
有3,616项
while Russia ranks second
而俄罗斯排在第二
with 2,695 items.
有2,695项
That sounds like a lot, right?
这听着不少了吧
But compared to subsequent sanctions, it's just a drop in the ocean.
哎这相对于之后的制裁就是毛毛雨
After the Russia-Ukraine war,
俄乌战争之后
the number of sanctions imposed on Russia increased tenfold,
俄罗斯被制裁的数量翻了10倍
exceeding 25,000.
超过了25,000项
Global countries imposed
全球各国对俄罗斯实施了有史以来
the largest and
规模最大
most numerous sanctions in history
项目最多的制裁
I roughly divide the sanctions against Russia
对俄罗斯的制裁
into several categories.
我大概分这么几大类
First, I think everyone can answer immediately
首先第一条我估计大家都会抢答了
those targeting individuals and entities.
就是针对个人和实体
Previously, most countries only
之前大部分国家哈
symbolically imposed these sanctions, but
这项就是象征性的
they were actually quite effective
但对俄罗斯来说
for Russia
还真是有点用
because Russia
因为俄罗斯
has many very wealthy oligarchs who
它真的是有很多很有钱的寡头富豪
keep their money in overseas banks
把钱放在海外的银行
or hide it overseas.
或者说把钱藏在海外的银行
This includes bank assets,
这里边有银行资产
apartments, and yachts.
有公寓有游艇
It's estimated that a total
据估算总共冻结了俄罗斯寡头
of $3 billion in assets belonging to Russian oligarchs has been frozen.
30亿美元的资产
While this amount
这点钱呢
may seem small in the grand scheme of things
虽然从宏观层面上来说啊
The impact on Russia’s economy
对俄罗斯经济造成的打击
was certainly small in proportion.
肯定比例很小
But it did hit the top levels
但它确实非常精准的
and elites of Russia with
打击到了俄罗斯的高层
remarkable precision
俄罗斯的精英
even restricting their travel abroad.
还限制他们出国
These wealthy individuals are likely furious.
这富豪可能都气得牙痒痒啊
The second major sanction against Russia is SWIFT.
而对俄罗斯制裁的第二大招就是SWIFT
Most people are familiar with it
这个词儿估计大家都有所耳闻
SWIFT, short for Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication.
SWIFT全称叫做"环球银行金融电信协会"
Simply put,
简单来说
it's a standardised language
它是全球银行之间
for global
转账通信
interbank transfers
一个标准化的语言
For example, international transfers
比如说大家进行国际转账的时候
use a SWIFT code.
都会有一个Swift Code
The SWIFT system
这个SWIFT系统
connects over 11,000 entities worldwide
连接了全球超过11,000个实体
we won't go into detail today.
这个今天我们就不细说了哈
In short,
总之就是
most cross-border transfers between banks
绝大多数银行之间的跨境转账
must use the SWIFT standard.
都得用这套SWIFT的标准
Generally,
一般情况下
if you don't use SWIFT,
你要是不用这个SWIFT
the receiving bank won't accept it.
对方银行是不认的
As part of the sanctions,
作为制裁的一部分
there are 45 Russian banks
有45家俄罗斯的银行
and 4 Belarusian banks
和4家白俄罗斯的银行
have been banned from using SWIFT for international payments
被禁止使用SWIFT进行国际支付
effectively blocking most Russian banks.
这就相当于阻隔了俄罗斯大部分银行
Note that SWIFT doesn't completely block
跟海外的资金通道
overseas funding channels
注意啊它不是完全阻隔
After all, it's just a standardised language.
毕竟SWIFT只是一个标准化的语言
It’s like I’m cutting off your contact with the outside world
就好像我为了切断你跟外界的联系
I’m not locking you up
我不是说把你给关起来
or confiscate your phone
或者把你手机没收了
but many mainstream chat apps would become unusable
但是很多主流的聊天APP你不能用了
not even WeChat.
微信你不能用了
This way
这样一来
would significantly increase the cost
你想要跟别人联系
of contacting others.
成本一下就高很多
You'd either have to write a letter,
要么你写信对吧
make a phone call
或者打电话
or develop your own APP
或者你自己重新开发个APP
which would require the other party to cooperate by
然后你还得要求对方配合你
writing letters, making phone calls, or using your APP
写信打电话用你的APP
very inconvenient, right?
就很麻烦对吧
From a macro perspective, this inconvenience translates
而这种麻烦从宏观层面上来讲
into huge economic losses
就是巨大的经济损失
and costs.
经济成本
So how does Russia retaliate
那面临这种经济制裁
against such economic sanctions?
俄罗斯怎么反制呢
In fact, it developed its own system
他其实早在2014年
as early as 2014, the alternative to SWIFT
就开发了一套自己的SWIFT的替代系统
is called SPFS.
叫做SPFS
In the example we just discussed,
放在刚才咱们说那个例子里
it's like they developed their own
就是相当于他自己开发了
chat app.
一个聊天的APP
Developing such a system isn't difficult.
其实开发这么套系统并不难
SWIFT itself isn't user-friendly;
那个SWIFT本身我跟你说也不好用
it's slow and inefficient.
它慢 效率也不高
The key is that everyone uses it
那关键就是所有人都用它
creating a network effect.
它有它的网络效应
Even if Russia's SPFS system
就算俄罗斯这个SPFS系统
is well-developed,
它开发的再好
the biggest challenge is
最难的地方是
getting the other party’s banks to trust the system
让对方的银行也信任这个系统
and actually use it
也用这个系统
and that takes time.
这都需要时间
Currently about a quarter of cross-border payments
所以现在俄罗斯的跨境支付里头
in Russia use SPFS
大概是有1/4走的是这个SPFS系统
Other methods
其他的方式呢
include using
比如说你可以
a friendly third-country bank,
通过一个友好的第三国的银行
or cryptocurrencies
通过加密货币
they've also developed their own stablecoins
它也开发自己的稳定币
In general, excluding SWIFT
但总之排除SWIFT
has significant impact on Russia's financial system.
对俄罗斯资金链的打击还是挺大的
The third major sanction against Russia
对俄罗斯第三大制裁方向
is the freezing of official assets,
就是冻结官方资产
primarily
官方资产
the assets of the Russian central bank,
其实主要就是俄罗斯央行的资产
namely its foreign exchange reserves.
就是它的外汇储备
As mentioned earlier when discussing
其实我们刚才讲古巴
Cuba and Iran
伊朗的时候也带到了
the US and Europe
就是像美国欧洲
freeze all
它会把你们国家相关的
assets in banks and financial institutions
只要我能够的着的
within a country they
银行 金融机构里的资产
can reach
全都给冻结
This time,
这回俄罗斯被冻结
approximately $300 billion of Russia's assets were frozen,
大概有3,000亿美元
roughly half of its foreign exchange reserves.
占到了他外汇储备的大概一半
And do you know which country
而你知道他被冻结的钱
held the majority of this frozen money?
主要是在哪个国家吗
You probably wouldn't guess it
我估计你肯定想不到
it's Belgium
就是比利时
Why Belgium?
为什么是比利时呢
Because Russia's central bank and
你想俄罗斯它央行的钱
its foreign exchange reserves aren't all cash;
它的外汇储备不可能都是现金
they've purchased a large amount of financial assets.
它会买大量的金融资产
For example, European
比如说欧美的债券
and American bonds,
而这些债券
especially European bonds,
尤其是欧洲的债券
all need to be cleared
它都需要经过一家叫做Euroclear的公司
or managed
去做清算
by a company called Euroclear.
或者说托管
Therefore, the European bonds purchased by the Russian central bank
所以说俄罗斯央行买的欧洲债券
all had to go through the Belgian company Euroclear.
都必须经过比利时的公司Euroclear
Now, all of these have been frozen.
得这回全都被冻了
With the central bank's foreign exchange reserves frozen,
央行的外汇储备被冻了
it's difficult for it to freely adjust the exchange rate.
它就很难去自由的调节汇率
This is why you see the ruble falling so sharply
这也是为什么你看战争刚开始的时候
at the beginning of the war.
卢布跌得非常厉害
However, Russia has one major advantage
不过呢俄罗斯他有一点很厉害
it has a money-printing machine
就是他有印钞机啊
its energy resources.
就是他的能源
Russia's annual energy exports
你想俄罗斯一年的能源出口
can earn approximately $200-300 billion
大概能赚2,000-3,000亿美元
So, the freezing of $300 billion in its central bank's reserves has
所以它央行被冻了3,000亿
a significant short-term impact
短期影响很大
but frankly,
但说实在的
in the long run, it will not be difficult for it to recover.
长期它想缓过来其实并不难
The next direction of sanctions,
好那下一个制裁方向
is also the trade sanctions we mentioned earlier.
也是我们刚刚提到的贸易制裁
For Russia, it’s basically targeting its money-printing machine
对俄罗斯来说就是针对它的印钞机
oil and gas.
石油天然气
If you want to restrict Russian oil and gas,
如果你要限制俄罗斯的石油天然气
the sanctioning country also faces difficulties
这个对制裁国家他也有他的难处
The EU is far too dependent on
就是欧盟实在是太依赖
Russian energy.
俄罗斯的能源了
You see,
你要知道
previously 45% of its natural gas,
他之前45%的天然气
almost half, came from Russia.
将近一半都是来自俄罗斯
This is the kind of move that could hurt the enemy but end up hurting yourself even more
这就属于伤敌一千可能自损三千
Frankly,
说实在的
the EU just wanted to prove
欧盟也就是要争口气
itself, right?
对吧我得表态
So you see, in 2022,
所以你看2022年的时候
most European countries
绝大多数的欧洲国家
were also facing their own energy crises
也自己陷入了能源危机
And because Russia's natural
而且因为俄罗斯的天然气
gas and oil exports were so large,
石油出口量实在是太大了
the US and Europe didn't dare to directly ban them
欧美也不敢直接禁止
for fear of triggering a global energy crisis.
怕引发全球性的能源危机
So how did they finally decide to impose sanctions?
所以它最后决定怎么制裁呢
Russian can still export oil
就是俄罗斯你还是可以出口石油
but all seaborne oil shipments
但是所有海运的石油
were subject to a price cap.
必须得有个价格的上限
This cap was set at $60 per barrel
这个数字在2022年底
at the end of 2022,
定在了60美元一桶
roughly 85% of the market price at the time.
大概是当时市场价的八五折
The aim was
你看他就想通过这种方式
to restrict Russian revenue
一方面可以限制俄罗斯的收入
without significantly impacting
同时又不至于对全球的能源价格
global energy prices .
产生太大的影响
And do you know who the biggest beneficiary was?
而这里头你知道最大的受益国是谁吗
We've mentioned it multiple times
我们刚才其实提到了好几次
It's india
就是印度
When the West first proposed sanctions on Russian oil,
西方刚开始要制裁俄罗斯原油的时候
India objected,
印度就跳出来了
saying, "you can impose sanctions
说什么制裁
but I won't!
你们制裁 我不制裁啊
I don't agree to the price cap! "
什么价格上限我不认
As a result, India began
于是印度就开始
importing large quantities of Russian energy,
大量的进口俄罗斯的能源
roughly 20 times the amount it imported before the war.
大概是战前它从俄罗斯进口数量的20倍
Actually, for the past 2 years
其实这两年
you can see that India's economy has developed very rapidly
你看印度经济发展的非常快
which is largely related
哎这其实跟俄罗斯廉价的能源输入
to the cheap energy imports from Russia
是有很大关系的
Of course,
当然了
India's non-participation in sanctions also has its costs.
印度不参加制裁肯定也是有成本
What are these costs?
成本是什么呢
Secondary sanctions.
就是二级制裁
Look at the US
你看美国
this year, it first imposed a 25% basic tariff on India,
今年先是给印度加了25%的基本关税
and a few days ago Trump said that
前两天特朗普又说了
because India bought so much Russian oil
因为你买了那么多俄罗斯的石油
and did not comply with the price cap
还不遵守价格上限
he would impose an additional 25% tariff on it
所以我额外再给你加25%的关税
In general,
总的来说呢
one of the ways Russia circumvents
西方对俄罗斯进行贸易制裁
Western trade and
原油制裁
oil sanctions
俄罗斯规避的方式之一
is by selling to India
就是卖给印度
and China.
卖给中国
Its energy exports will certainly be suppressed
他能源出口肯定会被抑制
but it still has considerable revenue
但还是有不少的收入
which has become an important source of income
这个也成了它抵抗制裁的
for it to resist sanctions.
重要经济来源
At the same time, Russia also engages in a lot of smuggling
同时呢俄罗斯也会进行很多的走私
This is the border between Georgia and Russia.
你看这个是格鲁吉亚和俄罗斯的边境
The long line of trucks here
这排着大长队的货车
is all waiting to trade with Russia.
全都是等着跟俄罗斯进行贸易的车
Hidden among them are many
这里头其实藏了很多
luxury cars like Mercedes-Benz and BMW, which are subject to sanctions.
像是什么奔驰宝马这种被制裁的豪车
If you only look at official data,
你要是单看官方数据的话
you'll see that
你就会发现
Georgia's trade deficit in the past two years
这两年格鲁吉亚的贸易逆差
is alarmingly high.
怎么这么吓人
Its imports far exceed its exports.
就是它的进口量要远远大于出口
Why?
为什么呀
Well, not only have imports increased, but
哎其实人家不光是进口增加了
exports have also increased.
出口也增加了
However, these are all smuggled into Russia and
只不过他都是偷偷运到俄罗斯的
not recorded in the official accounts,
没有记在官方的账上
so the officially reported
所以官方显示出来的
trade deficit appears significantly larger.
贸易逆差就明显增加
In essence, this means
其实这就相当于
Russia is using Georgia for transshipment
俄罗斯通过格鲁吉亚转口贸易
to evade sanctions.
来躲避制裁
Besides the official sanctions
除了刚才咱们说的
we just mentioned, Russia
俄罗斯受到那些官方制裁
has also been impacted by another factor
它其实还受到了一个冲击
You could also call it a sanction, which
你也可以把它叫做制裁
I find quite interesting.
我觉得还挺有意思
It's a self-sanction from overseas companies.
就是来自海外企业的自我制裁
Many Western multinational brands,
就是很多西方的跨国品牌
even though they can still operate legally in Russia
虽说我还是能在俄罗斯合法经营
are worried about public opinion risks
但是呢他们担心一些舆论风险
so they say, "I have to withdraw."
就说哎不行我得撤
They sanction themselves by
纷纷自己把自己给制裁了
moving their businesses out of Russia.
把业务搬出俄罗斯
Imagine, within a week,
你就想象一个礼拜之内
all the big brands we're familiar with are gone,
大家生活中熟悉的那些大品牌全没了
all closed down.
全关门了
The impact is quite significant.
这其实影响还是挺大的
However, if you think about it carefully,
不过呢你仔细想一想啊
it doesn't mean that
这其实并不代表说
a vacuum immediately appeared in these industries.
这些行业立刻就出现了真空
The original physical stores,
因为原来的那些实体店
employees,
那些员工
and supply chains are still there;
那些产业链都还在
the companies have left.
公司撤走了
But what can Russia do?
但是俄罗斯可以怎么样呀
It can change the name but not the substance.
它可以换汤不换药
I can go with the original team.
我可以原班人马
immediately set up a new Russian knock-off
立刻成立一个新的俄罗斯山寨版
and continue operating
继续运营
So at this time
所以那时候
There are many
俄罗斯就出现了挺多
comical knock-off brands appeared in Russia.
看起来有点搞笑的山寨品牌
The original Starbucks became Stars Coffee,
原来的Starbucks变成了Stars Coffee
Zara became Maag
Zara变成了Maag
Coca-Cola became Dobri Cola,
Coca Cola变成了Dobri Cola
and many more.
反正等等吧
We've discussed so many examples
你看咱们刚才说了这么多例子
but there's a fundamental principle about sanctions
其实有一个关于制裁的底层规律
which is that sanctions
就是这个制裁
are often more effective in the short term.
它往往是短期的威慑力更强
Economic sanctions
经济制裁
frequently catch countries off guard.
很多时候它打的就是一个措手不及
Once the sanctioned country recovers and
等被制裁国缓过来了
adjusts, and
调整过来了
a new system is established,
新的系统形成了
the marginal effect diminishes sharply.
它的边际效果就会骤减
Look at why sanctions against Cuba and North Korea
你看为什么制裁对象古巴 朝鲜
haven't had such a significant impact.
没那么大作用
They've been under sanctions for years and
他们制裁那么多年了
have long since recovered
早就缓过来了
They've figured out their economic structures, resource channels,
什么经济结构 资源渠道 替代方案
and alternative solutions,
全都已经搞明白了
so they're not so afraid of sanctions.
所以也没有那么怕你制裁
The two successful negotiations between the US and Iran
而美国跟伊朗两次谈判的成功
were both quite sudden,
其实都是足够的突然
catching Iran off guard.
给伊朗来了个措手不及
As for Russia,
而俄罗斯呢
although Western sanctions seem sudden
虽然感觉上西方对他的制裁是突发的
but you can see that Russia
但其实你看俄罗斯从2014年
secretly began preparing to counter them as early as 2014.
就开始秘密的准备去应对西方的制裁
Sanctions are most effective when
制裁它是在刚刚启动的时候
the sanctioned country
被制裁国
hasn't yet formed a complete alternative system;
还没有形成一个完整的替代系统
this is when the impact is highest
打击度是更高的
There is a strong incentive
这个时候是有最大的激励
to make concessions and negotiate,
去完成让步和谈判的
but if no agreement is reached at the beginning,
而一旦最开始没达成协议
the longer the sanctions drag on,
这个时间一拖下去
the less they
制裁就会越来越少的
suppress the elites of the sanctioned country
压制被制裁国的精英
and the more they suppress the lower classes .
而只会持续压制底层民众
It becomes difficult to reach an effective agreement,
又很难有效的达成协议
leading to a stalemate.
形成一个僵局
Academically, this
这个在学术上说
creates "sanction fatigue."
就形成了一个"制裁疲劳"
Once sanctions fatigue forms,
而一旦制裁疲劳形成
both the sanctioning and sanctioned countries
不管是制裁国还是被制裁国
will have a group of vested interests,
其实都会形成一批既得利益者
making it even more difficult to lift sanctions.
想要取消制裁就会变得更加困难
This
如此一来
creates a vicious cycle of sanctions,
就形成了一个制裁的怪圈
ultimately evolving
最终就会演变成
into endless, slow oppression of the lower classes .
对底层大众无止境的慢性压制
Actually, I've researched a huge amount of information and data on
其实吧针对今天咱们讲到的
each of the sanctioned countries
每个被制裁的国家
we've discussed today
我都查了巨量的信息和资料
However, to maintain a clear structure,
但是呢为了保持这个结构主线清晰
a manageable length
时长比较可控
and easy-to-understand language
又通俗易懂
I've omitted many details and contents.
确实很多细节和内容都被我忽略了
Of these countries,
这些国家里头
we've already discussed Russia and Iran;
你看咱们讲过的是俄罗斯和伊朗
I will definitely tackle the rest one by one.
剩下的我一定会逐个击破的
That's all for today.
这话就撂这了